A Guide to the The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection, 1962-1971
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection, 1962-1971
Fairfax County Public Library
0.5 linear feet
The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection contains 141 photographs and six negatives from 1962-1971. The images depict a quickly developing Fairfax County suffering from erosion and other environmental problems, and conservation efforts to combat them.
Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dan Schwartz, Northern Virginia Soil & Water Conservation District, December 2023.
Historical and Biographical Information
In July 1945, the Virginia Soil Conservation Committee approved the establishment of the Northern Virginia Soil Conservation District which included Loudoun, Prince William and Fairfax counties. Those three counties voted for its creation in a referendum held on April 26, 1945. Renamed the Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District (NVSWCD) on July 1, 1964, it was established to develop a public understanding of the need for planning and action to preserve natural resources; to encourage landowners to use the most effective practices and procedures in the conservation of soil and natural resources; and to assist landowners and operators with conservation. The District was also concerned about the consequences of erosion, flooding and sedimentation caused by the sudden increase in land development and construction.
A board of five supervisors directed the work of the District assisted by professional personnel of the Soil Conservation Service of the Department of Agriculture. The offices were originally located in Manassas, then at 114 East Main Street at Fairfax Circle, and later in January 1970, the District moved to 3945 Chain Bridge Road in Fairfax. Today, its offices are in the Fairfax County Government Center.
Following World War II, the rural character of Fairfax County was rapidly changing due to the influx of people seeking housing and the related expansion of shopping centers, roads, schools, and recreation. The hasty development brought about staggering damage and destruction to many irreplaceable natural resources and it caused abundant soil and water conservation problems.
Originally orientated toward agriculture, the District undertook a pilot urban conservation program in Fairfax County beginning in July 1962, with the intent of minimizing and preventing further destruction. Glenn B. Anderson of the Soil Conservation Service was assigned to the District to assist with the pilot project over the next decade. Subsequently, the District undertook many initiatives including developing a conservation policy for the county, conducted field tours outlining major conservation problems and the techniques used to alleviate them, various planting projects, conducted environmental studies and assessments at the request of county agencies, provided consultation services, assisted farmers with conservation practices and projects, and provided conservation outreach to the public. The District celebrates 80 years of promoting soil and water conservation in Fairfax County in 2025.
Scope and Content
The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection contains 141 photographs and six negatives from 1962-1971. The images depict a quickly developing Fairfax County suffering from erosion and other environmental problems, and conservation efforts to combat them. The photographs were taken to increase public understanding of the conservation needs and problems in Fairfax County. Some of these images were originally published in the District’s annual reports and were mostly photographed by Glenn B. Anderson, the District Conservationist; Gordon S. Smith, an information specialist of the Soil Conservation Service based in Upper Darby, PA; and Clarence Deland, a field photographer for the Soil Conservation Service. Locations featured include Annandale, Burke, Centreville, Chantilly, Fairfax, Falls Church, McLean, Seven Corners, Springfield, Tysons Corner, and Vienna, VA.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Anderson, Glenn B. (1926-2008); Smith, Gordon S. (1899-1978); Soils -- Virginia.; Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District; Soil erosion - Virgina; Soil erosion -- Virginia -- Fairfax County; Soil conservation -- Virginia -- Fairfax County
Container List
- Annandale Woods Subdivision, Annandale, VA: An area of land where high density urban development is being permitted on slopes that exceed 15%. The roadbank in the foreground is over 25 feet high, and individual sewage lines are often excavated to a depth of 20 feet. This type of land use results in excess cost to developers and compounds soil and water conservation problems. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1964 September 3
- Annandale Woods Subdivision, Annandale, VA: This picture shows development of residential subdivision on steep land. The units under construction will have a 15 to 20" fill when completed. Development of steep slopes often results in excessive cost to builders and compounds soil and water conservation problems. [2 copies] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1964 September 3
- Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: [No caption] Men sitting in front of "Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve" sign. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 October ?
- Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Dwarf sorghum is one of the big crops on the Mitchell's hunting farm. This variety has a strong stem that withstands winter wind and snow to provide wildlife food during the winter. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 October 22
- Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Most of Phillip Mitchell's open land is laid out in contour strips 25 feet wide with 200 feet between strips. Strips are planted with corn, sorghum, buckwheat, flax or other cover and food-producing plants. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 October 22
- Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Mr. and Mrs. Phillip Mitchell and son - A family scene on this 255 acre recreation development where approximately 100 acres of crop land has been converted to the reduction of wildlife feed and cover crops. Mrs. Mitchell and son are displaying two neatly processed ring-necked pheasants. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 October 27
- Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Initial planting of special wildlife feed and cover plants on converted farm croplands. The plantings are arranged in strips for conservation purposes and hunter and dog accessibility. This farm consists of 265 acres and will be open for hunting for the first time this season. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1962 May
- Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: A 40' x 200' holding pen for ring neck pheasants. This pen is located in a convenient but secluded area of this 265 acre shooting preserve. Several thousand birds are stocked in this pen during the shooting season. Most of the structural materials were harvested from the farm. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1962 October
- Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: A 40' x 200' holding pen for ring neck pheasants. This pen is located in a convenient but secluded area of this 265 acre shooting preserve. Several thousand birds are stocked in this pen during the shooting season. Most of the structural materials were harvested from the farm. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1962 October
- Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Use of regular farming equipment for maintenance and other work on this 265 acre shooting preserve. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1962 October
- Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Young bird dog being trained. This 265 acre commercial shooting preserve will offer a wide variety of outdoor recreation activities, such as; shooting lessons, training dogs, boarding dogs, organized hunts for ringnecked pheasants, quail, and other upland game. [2 copies] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1963 October 4
- Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Part of the facilities and land use on a 265 acre commercial shooting preserve. The holding pen located in the clearing has capacity for several thousand ring-neck pheasants. Both field and contour strips located in the background contain plantings of special wildlife food and cover plants. Perennial wildlife borders are located along fence rows, woodlands and roadways. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Portions of a 265 acre commercial shooting preserve that has recently been taken out of crop production. Emphasis is placed on sound conservation use and treatment of the land. Wildlife food and cover plantings are arranged in field and contour strips. Perennial wildlife borders are located along the edge of wooded areas and road ways. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Congressional School, Falls Church, VA: A newly landscaped and eroded playground that has well prepared for seeding. The application of a simple mechanical conservation measure (diversion terraces) would have prevented much of this erosion and waste. The surface water could have been led to a safe outlet and a potential drainage problem prevented on the playground below. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1962 July 20
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: This high altitude, vertical photo covers most of the 10,000 acres involved in the new jetport. The floodwater dam and reservoir are not shown. The lake near the center of the photo serves as part of the landscaping and a drainage area for the terminal building area today. (photographer: FAA), 1962 November
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: The portion of the flood control impoundment on the Horsepan Run. The picture shows the top of the conduit during flood stage. This dam impounds water from a 15,000 acre watershed. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1963 March 6
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: FAA supervising horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin and SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson studying soil and agronomy problems on the 10,000 acre airport. Sound soil and water conservation planning and application is a must on urban areas like this. Urbanization of agricultural lands frequently compounds soil, water and related conservation problems. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: FAA supervising horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin and SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson studying soil and agronomy problems on the 10,000 acre airport. Sound soil and water conservation planning and application is a must on urban areas like this. Urbanization of agricultural lands frequently compounds soil, water and related conservation problems. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: FAA supervising horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin and SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson studying soil and agronomy problems on the 10,000 acre airport. Sound soil and water conservation planning and application is a must on urban areas like this. Urbanization of agricultural lands frequently compounds soil, water and related conservation problems. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Glenn Anderson, SCS technician for Fairfax County, left, and Gilbert J. Tobin, horticulturalist for Dulles Airport, examine new growth on loblolly pines planted on the outer fringes of the airport. The tree plantings are part of the 1000-foot-wide buffer zone around the airport. Over two million trees have been planted in this zone. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Now part of the landscaping near the terminal buildings, this 10-acre lake served as a de-silting basin during the construction period. The main terminal building's catch-basin roof and surrounding acreage keep the lake full. Prolonged dry spells in the past two years have made this lake a valuable source of irrigation water. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Part of the Dulles International Airport installation. This airport is located on approximately 10,000 acres of land most of which was in woodland and pasture land prior to urbanization. A basic conservation plan was employed during and after construction of this airport. Cooperation between SCD, Federal, State and County agencies often save the taxpayer thousands of dollars. [7 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson and FAA horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin discussing agronomy problems on the Dulles Airport grounds. The adverse soil conditions found in this area, coupled with tremendous land disturbance due to construction work, compounds the soil, water and plant material problems. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Two airport workers spread mulch in a planting of azalea shrubs near the terminal building. In the background are a few Washington hawthorne trees that form part of the new landscaping. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Up-stream aerial view at the Horse Pen Run flood control dam. This conservation structure provides flood protection to hundreds of down-stream land owners on Broad Run during and following periods of heavy rainfall. In the background can be seen the Dulles Administration Building and runways. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1964 June 25
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: [No caption] Dulles Airport construction. (photographer: Unknown), 1964 September
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: [No caption] Tractor in front of terminal building. (photographer: FAA), 1964 September
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Construction scene, building foundation. (photographer: Unknown), Undated
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Laying cornerstone for taxiway at Dulles International Airport. (photographer: FAA), Undated
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Pictured at the flood control dam at Dulles Airport during the suburbia conservation tour sponsored by the Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Tuesday (May 2) are these assistants to members of the House of Representatives, left to right: Jack McKee (Rep. Vigorito, Pa.); Jerr James (Rep. Belcher, Okla.); Mickey Holmes (Rep. Poage, Tex.); Ray Marbles (Rep. Marsh, Va.); Wayne Trotter (Rep. Wampler, Va.); and Bill Williams (Rep. Scott, Va.). (photographer: Unknown), Undated
- Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Taken during the November 22nd Conservation Field Tour. Shows group looking at FAA Dulles Flood Prevention Dam. (photographer: Ted James), Undated
- George Mason College, Fairfax, VA: [No caption]. Man looking at drain. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- George Mason College, Fairfax, VA: A twelve foot gully caused by uncontrolled storm runoff. An underground storm sewer no longer functions because it is completely blocked by silt from the unprotected and eroding areas. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Glen Burnie Park, Glen Burnie, MD: Erosion problems of this community area. The pool has been constructed by the community. (photographer: Bob Halstead), 1963 July 19
- Green Acres Elementary School, Fairfax, VA: Serious erosion damages on the Green Acres Elementary School construction site. Application of simple erosion control practices would greatly reduce damage to both the construction site and the down-stream properties located along Pohick Creek. (Pohick Creek Watershed) (photographer: Clarence Deland), 1968 June 26
- James W. Robinson Secondary School, Fairfax, VA: Heavy sediment deposits that has been conveyed through the storm sewer and deposited below outlet. No effective erosion control practices have been installed on this 79 acre site. Construction started in November 1969. The area drains into impoundment site #4. (Pohick Watershed) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1970 February
- James W. Robinson Secondary School, Fairfax, VA: Heavy silt deposits that have been conveyed through the storm sewer and deposited down below outlet. No effective erosion control practices have been installed on this 79 acre development. Construction started in November 1969. The area drains into impoundment site #4. (Pohick Watershed) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1970 February
- Lake Braddock, Burke, VA: [No caption] Proof prints and negatives of Lake Braddock. (Pohick River Watershed) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1971
- Lake Fairfax, Reston, VA: Some of the recreational facilities found on this 100-acre converted farm are a 30-acre lake, two large swimming areas, large picnicking area, camping area, restaurant, and many other facilities. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1964 September
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: This 200 year old Elm tree was the first the bulldozer assaulted. (photographer: Unknown), 1965
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: Langley High School construction. (photographer: Unknown), 1965 March
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: Langley High School construction. (photographer: Unknown), 1965 March
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: Langley High School construction. (photographer: Unknown), 1965 March
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), Undated
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), Undated
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), Undated
- Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), Undated
- Montgomery Ward - Seven Corners, 6100 Arlington Boulevard, Seven Corners, VA: Use of semi-permanent vegetative cover for erosion control on a commercial development. Land Grading was completed on this area during August 1963. This practice has proven to be both economical and effective for the control of accelerated soil erosion on urban developments where construction has been delayed. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 1967 September
- Montgomery Ward - Seven Corners, 6100 Arlington Boulevard, Seven Corners, VA: Diversion ditch above a 40' high cut. A concrete flume conveys the water to an underground storage sewer below. [3 copies and negative] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), Undated
- Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Conservation Awards, Unknown: [No caption] Award Ceremony: Dr. Stephen I. Granger, Stanley Lickey, Chairman Nelson Craun, Kettler Brothers Inc., House Brothers. (photographer: Unknown), 1967
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Two men inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Two men inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Houses at 5505 Ravenel Lane and 5507 Ravenel Lane. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Houses in Ravensworth subdivision. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Portions of a 28 acre Industrial Development where temporary vegetation is being established for erosion control. Vegetation is effective for the control of erosion on urban developments when application is done immediately following rough grading. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Unprotected soil from the 100-acre industrial development has washed out under new curbing flooding backyards of homes with silt. Proper protective measures could solve this situation. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 1966 March 16
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Glenn B. Anderson and Hugh Mackey. A section of newly seeded bank that partially surrounds this 109-acre industrial park. This fill slope was seeded to crown vetch and rye grass during early May 1968. About 4,000 linear feet of cut and fill slopes are located on this industrial complex. Some of these slopes are 40 feet in height. A stream valley park is located along the Flag Run, below this bank. (photographer: Clarence Deland), 1968 June 26
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Glenn B. Anderson and Hugh Mackey. Conservationist examining vegetative mulch for erosion control. The bare subsoil was seeded to temporary vegetation in the spring of 1966, following rough grading. This is part of a 109 acre industrial development which will be built on at a later date. (photographer: Clarence Deland), 1968 June 26
- Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Glenn B. Anderson and Hugh Mackey. Excellent erosion control by use of temporary vegetation. This is the 2nd year's growth of temporary vegetation which was seeded on rough graded subsoil for erosion control. It is a most effective and economical erosion control practice if used immediately after rough grading is done. This is part of a 109-acre industrial park which is to be built on a later date. (photographer: Clarence Deland), 1968 June 26